Guide to the David S. Brown papers, 1915-1989 MS0001.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Scrapbooks, 1915-1985; MS0001 Series 11; 50 Linear feet
  - Scrapbook 7, 10/1944 --08/1947 (Box 50)
    The cover of this blue scrapbook (12" x 10" x 2") has a picture of the shoulder patch for the VB-89 squadron, to which Brown belonged. In addition to letters, articles and photos chronicling the Browns' family life during this period. The scrapbook contains a significant amount of historical material. Among the artifacts are the actual patch from the VB-89 worn in World War II by Brown, a Civilian Army Pass, a Selective Service Registration Certificate from October 16, 1940, a war ration book, a newspaper photo (unknown source) of General McArthur at the Japanese surrender after WWII, Japanese money issued during the American occupation, and pictures taken in Japan during the occupation. Also included are a certificate from the Office of Scientific Research and Development issued March 1, 1945 commending Ms. Brown's contribution to WWII, and a "Plank Owner's Certificate" from the USS Antietam issued to Brown January 28, 1945 as a member of the ship's original crew. An issue of the USS Antietam Go-Get-'Am-Gazette (July 1945, Vol. I, No. 5) is also included. Another significant item is a rectangular piece of cloth printed with the American flag and a statement in French and oriental languages that begins "I am an American aviator. My plane was destroyed." The career of Robert A. Lovett is also chronicled in this scrapbook. Included are a September 18, 1945 New York Times article, "Stimson Resigns as War Secretary - Patterson Named" in which it is mentioned that Lovett resigns as Assistant Secretary of War for Air as well as various unidentified newspaper clippings detailing Dean Acheson's resignation and Lovett's appointment as Under Secretary of State under President Truman. An 8 x 10 photograph pictures Under Secretary Robert Patterson, Assistant Secretary John J. McCloy, Secretary Stimson, Assistant Secretary of Air Lovett and Special Assistant Harvey Bundy. In addition, two reproductions of documents are included, one of a letter signed by President Truman citing Lovett for Distinguished Service medal and one of the certificate awarding Lovett the medal on September 13, 1945, signed by Stimson and the Major General at the time.
  - Scrapbook 8, 01/1946 --02/1949 (Box 51)
    This is a brown scrapbook (9.50" x 11.75" x 2"). In addition to numerous family photos, cards and telegrams, the birth certificate of the Brown's second son Christopher Lovett Brown born October 30, 1948 at Columbia Hospital Washington, D.C. Also contained in the book are numerous photographs of Washington D.C. landmarks such as Kenmore in Fredericksburg, Virginia, the home of George Washington's sister, Betty Lewis, Woodlawn, Home of Nellie Curtis Lewis, stepdaughter of George Washington, and Oak Hill near Oatlands, Virginia, home of James Monroe designed by Thomas Jefferson. Aerial photographs taken from Brown's plane include the housing development of Park Fairfax in Alexandria, Virginia, Mount Vernon, the Washington D.C. monument area, Bailey's Cross-roads Airport, the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier and Arlington Cemetery. An article on Park Fairfax from The Star is also included. Finally, a photograph of the landscaping plans for the new State Department by landscaper Hagermann is also included. Of significance are numerous newspaper clippings and newspaper photographs as well as actual photographs of Robert A. Lovett, George C. Marshall, Ambassador Rober D. Murphy and President Harry S. Truman in various meetings on foreign aid and policy testifying before the Senate on the Marshall Plan. A page from Time magazine, March 29, 1948, entitled "National Affairs" details America's international affairs after WWII. The 1949 presidential inauguration of Harry S. Truman is chronicled through many newspaper photographs of the ceremonies and parade. Also included is an invitation to the ceremonies, a seating plan of the President's platform, ceremonial and parade programs as well as an identifying "Inaugural Committee" medallion. A newspaper photograph with caption pictures the inaugural protest of some D.C. residents lobbying for votes in the presidential election. Miscellaneous historical events are included such as a newspaper photograph of Princess Ashraf, sister to the then Shah of Iran during her visit to Washington, D.C., an article dated November 1947 on the appointment of Dr. Samuel D. Marble at age 31 to the presidency of Wilmington College, making him the youngest college president at the time and a photograph of an early TV broadcast. Also included are a program from the National Symphony Orchestra Benefit performance for the opening of the Playhouse Theatre, April 27, 1948, obituaries of G. F. Scherer, Embassy aid in Mexico city and W. A. Jump, Director of Finance at USDA, and Ruth Flumo political cartoons. Finally the front section of the New York Times, January 22, 1946, is included with the headline story "President's Message On The State of the Union and Transmitting the Budget."
  - Scrapbook 9, 02/1949 --12/1949 (Box 52)
    A brown scrapbook (9.25" x 11.75" x 1.50") that, in addition to family photos and Christmas cards, contains material from the June 7, 1949 meeting of the 3rd Assembly of the International Civil Aviation Organization in Montreal, Canada. Brown"s invitation to the event, a certificate from the US State Department naming Brown an advisor to the Assembly, and a photograph of the Assembly are included. The book also contains Brown's invitation to a National Air Council meeting in Washington, D.C. on the topic "Economic Consequences of Air Power" held at the Library of Congress March 7, 1949. In addition, newspaper clippings about James Forrestal, including a May 23, 1949 article from the Evening Star chronicle his career and suicide of that year. An August 9, 1949 article from the Washington Daily News entitled "No Politics Behind B-36, Lovett Says" details the Senate investigation into the Wartime orders for the B-36 bomber. Two newspaper photographs of Prince Charles of England at age 8 months and one year as well as a December 3, 1949 obituary for the Playwright Phillip Barry are also included.
  - Scrapbook 10, 02/1950 --08/1951 (Box 53)
    A maroon scrapbook (9.5" x 11.75" x 1.75") chronicling the Brown's family life during the period as well as national events upto the start of the Korean war. Numerous family photos and cards are included from family vacations. The birth of the Brown's third son, Robert Lovett Brown on January 26, 1951 at Columbia Hospital, Washington, D.C. is noted through his birth certificate, announcements, and telegrams. The Brown's first home in Fairfax County Virginia is pictured and a "Home Location Survey" for it are in the scrapbook. Also, a newspaper article about the sub-division, "Belle View", site of the Brown's home, is included. Brown's itinerary for his trip to Europe in August 1951 as an employee of the Economic Cooperation Committee (ECA) is included. Also contained in the scrapbook is an article on William Foster's appointment to Chief of ECA, articles on Robert A. Lovett's appointment to Deputy Defense Secretary in 1950, programs and a ticket from the 195l christening of the USS United States in Newport News, Virginia, a program cover from the Aviation Education Conference in 1950 to which Brown was a consultant, some of Brown's articles and writings from the period, and an invitation to the midpoint anniversary observance of the Marshall Plan on April 3, 1950. Finally, an article on Princess Dayan Djavidan, widow of Khedive Abbass Hilmi, former King of Egypt, and a Saturday Evening Post cover from January 7, 1950 picturing Congress in session are included. The last page of the book contains a newspaper photo of Robert A. Lovett as Defense Secretary, Senator Hoyt S. Vanberg as Air Force Chief and Thomas Finletter as Secretary of Air Force travelling to the White House for a meeting on the "Critical Situation in Korea."
  - Scrapbook 11, 09/1951 --04/1952 (Box 53)
    A blue scrapbook (9.5" x 11.75" x 1.5") containing family photos of vacations and holidays as well as extensive material on Robert A. Lovett's succession of G. C. Marshall as Secretary of Defense in September 1951. Included in the book are a cover of a New York Times magazine from September 23, 1951 picturing Robert A. Lovett, articles on the subsequent reorganization of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, a newspaper article from Rio de Janerio, September 14, 1951, on Robert A. Lovett's appointment. Among the other items that commemorate Robert A Lovett's promotion include two black and white photographs of Robert A. Lovett being sworn in and standing near George C. Marshall, another black and white photograph from an interview picturing Robert A. Lovett and his wife, as well as an article about Robert A. Lovett in U. S. Air Services magazine in October 1951. There are several newspaper, colored clippings picturing Mrs. Lovett in various fashionable outfits as well as Brown's invitation to the White House on October 31, 1951. Newspaper photos from the visit of the then princess Elizabeth of England to Washington in October 1951 are included along with an obituary for King George Vi, her father, newspaper photos of his funeral and a full page color drawing of Elizabeth as Queen. Four 8 x 10 black and white photos of Churchill and Truman from 1952 as well as a photograph of a quest book with the signatures of Truman and Churchill are historically significant. An article on the Burgandy Farm School in Alexandria, Virginia describes educational ideas in vogue at the time. Finally, newspaper clippings detailing the firing of Attorney General McGrath by Truman are included.
  - Scrapbook 12, 04/1952 --12/1953 (Box 54)
    A red scrapbook with cream-colored binding (9"x11 3"x1 3/8") containing memorabilia from the Truman administration and from the 1952 presidential election as well as family photographs. Seven newspaper clippings captioned "The Changing White House" present historical views of the President's home and together with 11 magazine photographs, some in color of the "White House Redecorated," a before and after picture of the remodeling done by President and Mrs. Truman is presented. Other items from the Truman era include an invitation to the Truman Farewell on May 14, 1952, a pamphlet entitled "Unity, Strength, Freedom: A report to the Nation" from Armed Forces Day, May 17, 1952, and a map of Bolling Air Force Base made for the Armed Forces Day celebration there. Items from the 1952 Presidential campaign include newspaper clippings of Eisenhower after retiring from the armed forces, an 8 x 10 photograph of Eisenhower and Secretary of State Dean Acheson, an 8 x 10 photograph of Eisenhower at his retirement ceremony, memorabilia from the July 1952 Republican Convention including two colored drawings of Mamie and Dwight Eisenhower, and memorabilia from the Democratic Convention including a color drawing of Adalia Stevenson and his wife as well as drawings of other Democratic presidential nominees. An article from the Houston Post September 24, 1952 gives the text of the speech of the Republican Vice-President nominee, Richard Nixon made in responding to allegations of dishonesty about donations to his campaign. Two newspaper photographs of Eisenhower are included, one during his December 1952 trip to Korea and one of him and his wife at the victory celebration after the 1952 election. Miscellaneous historical events chronicled by the scrapbook include the building of a UN headquarters (newspaper photographs and articles), Queen Elizabeth of England's First Parliament (newspaper photograph), and the wedding of Anne D. Goodrich to Prince in exile Edmond Poniatowski of Poland in May 1952 (newspaper article). Family souvenirs include a program from the "1952 Scouting Exposition" at the DC Armory in May 1952, two 8 x 10 photographs of an unidentified man, perhaps Robert A. Lovett, receiving a degree, articles on Robert A. Lovett, Articles on the Burgandy Farm School, vacation pictures, the Brown children's artwork and letters to their parents.
  - Scrapbook 13, 01/1953 --12/1953 (Box 55)
    This red and cream-colored scrapbook (9" x 11 3/4" x 1 3/8") contains family photos, articles about the Brown children's schools and the birth certificate of Adele Quarterly? Brown born November 6, 1953. Of historical significance are newspaper clippings detailing the end of the Korean War, the April 1953 death of Queen Mary of England, and a series of five newspaper photographs entitled "It happened in 1953" depicting Ben Hogan winning the British Open Golf Tournament, Sir Edmund Hillary after climbing Mt. Everest, the Korean Truce, the 50th anniversary of the Wrights' flight at Kitty Hawk and the succession of Stalin by Malenkov as Soviet Premier. Also of interest are photographs from the 1953 inauguration as well as a program and ticket to the parade. The scrapbook includes a guest and contribution list from the "Eastern States Jefferson-Jackson Democrat Dinner" in February 1953, which gives David S. Brown's name as a guest. Underneath the guest list is the handwritten notation, "David was there - a guest if not a contributor. The publication of this list ended his government career a few months later (September 1953)." Two other items of interest are a March 1953 House and Garden pictorial featuring Robert A. Lovett's home and a colored newspaper photograph of Queen Frederika of Greece.
  - Scrapbook 14, 01/1954 --12/1954 (Box 55)
    This red and cream scrapbook (9" x 11 3/4" x 1 3/8") contains many family Christmas cards and photographs as well as interesting newspaper clippings. Significant clippings include a large (2 8 x 10 sheets) magazine photograph of the House of Representatives two minutes after Puerto Rican terrorists shot at the assembly in 1954, newspaper drawings of the hydrogen bomb test explosions of the year, a newspaper photo of the four minute mile barrier being broken by a runner. Other interesting items are a program from the Jefferson-Jackson Democratic Dinner 1954 that lists Brown as a guest, clippings from Brown's PHD dissertation, several newspaper articles stating that George Washington University had named Brown as an Associate Professor of Public Administration, newspaper photographs of Hurricane Carol in September 1954, and Brown's invitation to a Mexican Embassy reception and to a Saudi Arabian Embassy reception. A large 8 x 10 newspaper photograph of Albert Schweitzer building a hospital with the help of a native man is also included.
  - Scrapbook 15, 01/1955 --12/1957 (Box 56)
    This red and black scrapbook (13" x 15" x 3 3/8") contains some materials on George Washington University such as a newspaper photograph of a George Washington parking lot with a "Park it yourself" device, a newspaper article titled "GW Area Urban Renewal Ok'd", a program from George Washington University's Air Force Advanced Management Program, Convocation Exercises August 10, 1956 and 8 x 10 photographs of the same occasion, as well as clippings from a 1956 George Washington University publication titled "The University Faculty". Personal mementoes include 8 x10 photographs of Brown's PHD commencement at Syracuse University in June 1955 in addition to a complete 1955 issue of the Syracuse Daily Orange detailing the commencement and a program from the occasion. Family vacation photographs, articles by Brown and about Brown and his work with the Bakery and Confectioner Workers' Union, and a ticket to the July 10, 1956 All Star Game are also included. Of historical significance are a newspaper article on the polio vaccine, a newspaper picture of and article on the USS Forrestal, newspaper articles on Robert A. Lovett, newspaper articles on the August 1955 Summit as well as articles on President Eisenhower's heart attack and subsequent intestinal surgery. Also interesting are a January 1956 political pamphlet supporting the "Gray Plan" on school integration in Virginia and articles about that plan, a series of magazine clippings titled "Truman Memories", a color magazine photograph of Winston Churchill, one of Dr. Alexander Fleming who discovered penicillin, and one of Prince Rainier and Grace Kelly at their wedding. Two other items are newspaper articles on the demise of the cruise ship the Andrea Doria, and an invitation to Eisenhower's January 1957 Inaugural Ball.
  - Scrapbook 16, 02/1958 --07/1958 (Box 57)
    A black and red scrapbook (11 1" x 14 1" x 2 1") contains many pictures, postcards, pamphlets and itinerary plans from the Browns' tour of Belgium, France, Holland and Italy. A newspaper article and personal memorabilia record Brown's stint as a visiting professor at the Royal Institute of Science and Technology in Glasgow, Scotland. Included also are an article on the retiring of George Washington University president Marvin, a clipping from the Daily Scottish Mail May 30, 1958 on the sentencing of mass murderer Manuel, a newspaper picture of an oil tanker on the Potomac river sent to avoid a shortage during a winter storm in Washington and numerous articles on Burgandy Farm School. A certificate for Brown from the Chemical Corps School at Fort McClellan Alabama in 1958, a program from the 1958 Campaign Conference for Democratic Women, and a program from the 1958 "Conference on Politics" held at Georgetown University are also contained in this scrapbook.
  - Scrapbook 17, 07/1958 --12/1959 (Box 58)
    A black and red scrapbook (11" x 14 1" x 2 1") containing additional material (Photographs, tickets, postcards, etc.) from the Browns' European vacation, photographs of family and the children's camp, an obituary for Brown's father, and several playbills from the National Theater. Professional materials of Brown's include articles on the Baker's and Confectionery Workers' Union which employed Brown as a management advisor, as well as several 8 x 10 photographs of Brown giving lectures and at professional dinners, and a program from the Educational Buyers meeting held at George Washington University in October 1959 at which Brown was a speaker.
  - Scrapbook 18, 01/1960 --12/1960 (Box 59)
    A brown scrapbook (10 1" x 13 3" x 1 1") contains material on George Washington University such as an article of George Washington University professor Dr. Burnice Jarman for Korea, photographs of Brown's coworkers at George Washington University, an article on A. M. Woodruff who was then Dean of the School of Government at George Washington University, an article on the "Behavioral Science Center" at George Washington University, as well as a December 1960 issue of George Washington University's AFM Gazette. Family memorabilia includes programs and photographs from the Brown children's school athletic events and class pictures, family vacation photographs and playbills from the Arena Stage. Professional material of Brown's includes various programs from management training seminars at which Brown spoke such as the Army Medical Specialist Corps Supervisors course and the IRS Management Institute, and an 8 x 10 photograph of Brown and a group at the "US Treasury Law Enforcement Officers Training School". Of historical interest are a magazine photograph of the SSBN-GW captioned "World's First Missile Subs", articles on Robert A. Lovett, newspaper clippings about the engagement of Britain's Princess Margaret, 8 x 10 photographs from the Democratic Leaders Training Conference of 1960, articles on John F. Kennedy's presidential victory and a small card printed "Thank you for your help" and signed by John F. Kennedy in ink to Brown.
  - Scrapbook 19A, 04/1961 --07/1961 (Box 60)
    A brown scrapbook (10 1/4" x 13 1/4" x 1 1") containing photographs of the Brown family's travel in Pakistan, a pamphlet in Indian on manners for Pakistani and Indian travelers, a clipping from the Civil and Military Gazette of Lahore, Pakistan on the Institute of Public administration at which Brown taught for 18 months as well as 8 x 10 photographs and programs from the opening of the school and a program from the first commencement of the school.
  - Scrapbook 19B, 01/1961 --07/1961 (Box 60)
    A brown scrapbook (10 1/4" x 13 1/4" x 1 1/4") containing photographs from the Brown family's travels in Spain, Italy, Greece and Pakistan as well as an issue of George Washington University's AFAM Gazette in April 1961 with an article "Brown leaves for Pakistan". Of historical interest are tickets to the January 1961 Inauguration and Ball of John F. Kennedy, newspaper clippings on the new cabinet and an Inaugural program and engraved invitation to the occasion.
  - Scrapbook 19C, 07/1961 --04/1962 (Box 61)
    A black and red scrapbook (13" x 15" x 3 1/2") containing memorabilia from the Brown family's time in Pakistan. Included are many photographs of Pakistan and India, itineraries, newspaper clippings from Lahore, Pakistan papers, a copy of the Pakistani National anthem, several issues of LAS Times (Lahore American School newspaper), and an invitation to a reception for the King and Queen of Pakistan. Numerous satirical and professional writings of Brown's are included. Historically interesting are magazine photographs of the Kennedy family, clippings on Mrs. Kennedy's trip to Pakistan, and clippings on the "Space Race", the first manned orbit of earth and the Indian elections of 1962.
  - Scrapbook 20, 04/1962 --07/1962 (Box 62)
    A green scrapbook (12 1/4" x 15" x 1 1/2") containing additional photographs and memorabilia from the Brown family's stay in Pakistan. Included are a May 1962 issue of National Geographic, unpublished writings of Brown, several issues of Local News published by the US Information Service, as well as articles on the status of Pakistani women. Photographs from a Brown family trip to Thailand and of their departure from Pakistan on July 11, 1962 are also contained in the scrapbook along with several articles detailing Mrs. Kennedy's impression of Pakistan.
  - Scrapbook 21, 07/1962 --12/1962 (Box 63)
    This maroon scrapbook (12" x 15" x 1 1/2") contains family photographs of the Brown family's travels in the Philippines, Japan and Yellowstone National Park. Also included are photographs of the graduation of Brown's oldest son, David S. Brown Jr., from Mercuberg Academy, Pennsylvania. The Brown children's artwork and photographs of their sporting events are also present. In addition to Christmas cards, letters and photographs, the scrapbook contains numerous articles on India and on Pakistan, a campus guide to George Washington University and a copy of the George Washington University Federalist from fall 1962 that contains an article by Brown.
  - Scrapbook 22, 01/1963 --10/1963 (Box 63)